Guide to the Brooklyn Navy Yard oral history collection ARC.003
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Oral History Interview with Angelo DeSalvo, April 28, 2010; 2010.003.028
  During his interview, Angelo DeSalvo (1931- ) talks about enjoying the work he did, especially sea trials, and the camaraderie (and playful pranks) felt among coworkers. At the time of the USS Constellation fire, he recalls, he was home sick and saw it on TV. When he returned to the Navy Yard, he found his toolbox had "melted into one lump." DeSalvo also discusses the feeling in the Yard when its closing was announced and what happened to him and his coworkers afterward. At the end of the interview he remembers hearing of John F. Kennedy's assassination with his coworkers onboard a ship. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Warships; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Accidents; Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York Naval Shipyard; Constellation (Aircraft carrier)
- Oral History Interview with Shirleyann Dramer, April 1, 2009; 2010.003.008
  Shirleyann Mansdorf Dramer (1925- ) grew up in Brooklyn, New York, where she attended James Madison High School. After high school, Dramer attended Cooper Union where she studied science and later became a science teacher. At the time of the interview, Dramer was living in Merrick, Long Island.
  In the interview with Shirleyann Mansdorf Dramer (1925- ), she remembers stories about living and working in Brooklyn, with many additions from her two daughters, Kim and Brooke Dramer. Dramer remembers riding horses in Brooklyn on Ocean Parkway and taking hikes in the country after crossing the George Washington Bridge. She was on the bridge when she first heard about the attack on Pearl Harbor. Dramer recalls writing letters and sending food to soldiers overseas, as well as helping her mother drive an ambulance to pick up wounded soldiers at the Brooklyn Navy Yard and bring them to New York Methodist Hospital in Park Slope, Brooklyn. She remembers the security she encountered at the Brooklyn Navy Yard and interacting with injured soldiers at the Hospital. Dramer also reflects on the significant changes that took place in Brooklyn in the 1960s. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Family; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Long Island (N.Y.); Hospitals; Local transit -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Neighborhoods -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Security systems; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Transportation -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art; James Madison High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Wesley Fagan, March 11, 2011; 2010.003.029
  Wesley Fagan (1910- ) was born in Portsmouth, VA and has lived in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn since the 1950s. Fagan began playing the clarinet as a teenager and took up photography when his father gave him a Kodak box camera. He attended Clark College (now Clark Atlanta University), an historically black college, for two years but could not afford to continue. He moved to Buffalo, NY to play music with his uncle in the 1930s.While in Buffalo, Fagan attended a trade school and subsequently worked in the precision gauge lab of Buffalo Arms Service where he worked his way up from a porter to a machinist. He was in the Army from 1944-1946 and played in the Army band in Hawaii and Japan. After the war, he moved to Brooklyn because his sister was living there working as a nurse. Beginning as a messenger in the mailroom at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, Fagan later became the official photographer in the 1950s until the Yard closed in 1966. After the Yard was decommissioned, he went to work at the photo lab of the Fort Hamilton Army base. He later worked for the Manhattan Transit Authority as a railroad clerk.
  In this interview, Wesley Fagan (1910- ) talks about his youth and education, including his time at Clark College, The Julliard School, and Jermaine Photography School. Fagan goes into detail about his life as a musician, his work and colleagues at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, his family, marriages, raising four foster children, and his life in Brooklyn since the 1950s. At the Navy Yard, he photographed ships, damages and repairs, visiting dignitaries, ship christenings and launches, and the fire on the USS Constellation. During this time, he received many commendations for his work. Fagan also details the process of developing the photographs and the Navy's reluctance to catalog and store negatives and photographs, which were eventually discarded. He spent time as the lab photographer for the Materials Lab, which required a high level of clearance. Fagan often brings up ethnicity and race, including how this affected his work at the Navy Yard, and wishing that he had done more for Civil Rights. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Accidents; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Adoption; African Americans; African Americans |x Civil rights |x History |y 20th century; Musical instruments |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Musicians; Indians of North America; Warships; Photographers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Racism; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Soldiers; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Constellation (Aircraft carrier)
- Oral History Interview with Michael Faiella, July 31, 1987; 1995.005.003
  Michael Faiella (1928- ) grew up in Vinegar Hill, Brooklyn on Sands Street. His father opened Reliable Naval Tailoring, Co. in 1927 at 191 Sands Street. The shop moved several times, but always remained close to the Brooklyn Navy Yard.
  In his interview, Michael Faiella (1928- ) describes how Reliable Naval Tailoring, Co. changed over its 60 years tenure. The store sold uniforms to sailors, not the workers at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. Faiella also describes the important relationship between the Navy Yard and the Brooklyn community, and how much the neighborhood deteriorated after the Navy Yard was decommissioned. As the bars, restaurants and other uniform stores closed around Faiella, they were able to maintain business by diversifying their products and clientele. Faiella was also interviewed in 2007. Interview conducted by Benjamin Filene.
  Ethnicity; Sands Street (New York, N.Y.); Gravesend (New York, N.Y.); Vinegar Hill (New York, N.Y.); Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ethnicity; Friendship; Immigrants; Tailoring |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Military uniforms; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; World War, 1939-1945; United States. Navy; New York Naval Shipyard
- Oral History Interview with Michael and Vincent Faiella, January 23, 2007; 2010.003.009
  Michael Faiella (1928- ) grew up in Vinegar Hill, Brooklyn on Sands Street. His father opened Reliable Naval Tailoring, Co. in 1927 at 191 Sands Street. The shop moved several times, but always remained close to the Brooklyn Navy Yard. Michael Faiella's son, Vincent Faiella (1960- ) grew up in Gravesend, Brooklyn and currently lives in Red Bank, New Jersey.
  In this joint interview, Michael (1928- ) and Vincent Faiella (1960- ) look back on the Reliable Naval Tailoring, Co.'s history in Brooklyn before Vincent Faiella moved the business to Red Hook, New Jersey in 2006. Michael Faiella talks about his Italian background, growing up in Brooklyn close to his extended family, and his fondness for the area around the Brooklyn Navy Yard. Michael and Vincent Faiella also discuss the commercial and social activities on Sands Street and how much the neighborhood changed after the Navy Yard was decommissioned and the Brooklyn-Queens Expressway was built. Michael Faiella was also interviewed in 1987. Interview conducted by Daniella Romano.
  Business enterprises; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Gravesend (New York, N.Y.); Sands Street (New York, N.Y.); Vinegar Hill (New York, N.Y.); Flatbush Avenue (New York, N.Y.); Family-owned business enterprises -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Local transit -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Military uniforms; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Tailoring |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Transportation -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Yacht clubs |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Faiella, Vincent
- Oral History Interview with Anthony Ferrara, June 23, 2008; 2010.003.011
  Anthony Ferrara (1915- ) grew up in Lower Manhattan in Little Italy. His family owned a restaurant on Coney Island that they ran during the summer season. Anthony Ferrara moved to Brooklyn in 1944 and spent most of his life working in restaurants. Because of an ear injury, he received 4F status and was unable to serve during WWII.
  Anthony Ferrara (1915- ) began working at the Brooklyn Navy Yard in 1941, after meeting a Navy Yard supervisor at the restaurant he worked at on Sands Street. During his interview, he discusses his duties as a fire warden and how the cleanliness of his job often separated him from the other workers. He also expresses his disappointment and embarrassment about being unable to serve overseas due to his 4F status. Ferrara's position allowed him to observe many of the things happening in the yard, including the progress of the USS Missouri, the USS Iowa and several Landing Ship Tanks. Ferrara also describes security at the Navy Yard, and how on one cold day, a security guard's nose dripped into the lunch container he was inspecting for alcohol. He left the yard after a little over a year and after attempting to get rid of his 4F status, he returned to working in restaurants. Ferrara remained in Brooklyn until 1996 when he moved in with family on Long Island, New York. An excerpt of this interview is used on a tour of the Brooklyn Navy Yard. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Cranes, derricks, etc; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); East Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Long Island (N.Y.); Sands Street (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Emigration and immigration; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ethnicity; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Italian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Security systems; Shipfitting; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Iowa (Battleship); Missouri (Battleship: BB 63)
- Oral History Interview with Lucille Ford, December 11, 2007; 2010.003.012
  Lucille Butler Ford (1922- ) is an African American woman who grew up in Harlem and the Bronx. Soon after graduating from Wadleigh High School, Lucille Ford looked for work at the Brooklyn Navy Yard with a friend who was also from the Bronx. Two of Ford's brothers served during WWII. After leaving the Navy Yard in 1945, Ford began working for New York Telephone (now Verizon) and now lives in Long Island, New York.
  Lucille Butler Ford (1922- ) began working as a messenger at the Brooklyn Navy Yard and was soon trained as a clerk typist in Building 77. The interview focuses on social life at the Navy Yard and the close friendships that Ford formed during the three years she worked there. She also discusses the ethnic backgrounds and interaction between the female workers in Building 77, sharing a story about a Jewish friend wanting to visit Harlem and how her mother made greens when she visited. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan and Jennifer Egan.
  Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Bronx (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Dating (Social customs); Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Food; Local transit -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Navy-yards and naval stations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Security systems; Transportation -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Wages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; African American women; New York Naval Shipyard; Paul Laurence Dunbar Apartments, Inc.; Wadleigh High School (New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Helen Gagliardi, August 11, 2010; 2010.003.030
  Helen Sullivan Gagliardi (1925- ) grew up in Brooklyn. She was given her mother's last name (Sullivan) because her mother returned to her maiden name after getting a divorce because it was easier for unmarried women to find work during the Depression. Gagliardi attended PS203 in Brooklyn and then Saint Brendan's (Midwood, Brooklyn) for high school. She studied Chemistry at Brooklyn College where she earned a Master's and PhD, finishing all but her dissertation. She worked in the Brooklyn Navy Yard's chemistry lab from 1944-1945 when the war ended. After marrying, Gagliardi went on to teach science at PS208, an elementary school with a program for gifted students, from the 1960s until she retired in 1984. Upon retiring, she moved to California, near San Diego, where one of her two daughters lives. The Brooklyn Historical Society connected with Gagliardi because her other daughter, who lives in Boston, took her on the Brooklyn Navy Yard tour lead by Urban Oyster.
  In her interview, Helen Sullivan Gagliardi (1925- ) talks about her parents' marriage (Catholic - Protestant) and how both her mother and grandmother were strong, independent women who raised children on their own. She discusses the often limited opportunities available for women when she was in college, especially in her field of chemistry. She describes in great detail her work environment at the Brooklyn Navy Yard, including her coworkers and the lab in which she worked. The lab was trying to discover a method for creating synthetic rubber, which was much needed during WWII. When the war was over, the Navy discontinued the project, but private industry went on to use similar techniques to eventually discover hard and soft plastics that are abundant today. Gagliardi also discusses her recent experience visiting the Navy Yard, comparing the congestion of workers in the 1940s with the emptiness and open space she saw in her recent visit. She also recounts her experiences as a science teacher at PS208 in East Flatbush, Brooklyn. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Chemistry; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Long Island (N.Y.); Chemistry; Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Navy-yards and naval stations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Warships; Religion and ethics; Sex role; Sexism; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Women |x Employment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York Naval Shipyard
- Oral History Interview with Jack Grossman, May 4, 2010; 2010.003.031
  Jack Grossman (1923- ) was born in New York on the Lower East Side near the Williamsburg Bridge. His father emigrated from Austria and was known as the Pickle Man because he made and sold pickles. His mother passed away when he was four years old and he is the youngest of four children. In 1939 or 1940, Grossman was hired at the Brooklyn Navy Yard as a Trainee - he was only 17 years old so they had to give him a special title and paid him only 58 cents per hour. He later became a shipbuilder and attended classes three days a week to learn how to tack weld and read ship blueprints.
  In his interview, Jack Grossman (1923- ) talks about growing up in Brooklyn in a Jewish family and his experience working at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. He describes in detail the Mold Loft at the Navy Yard, where balsawood models were made from the blueprints and then steel was heated in large ovens and shaped to match the models, forming the curved pieces that would become part of the hull of the ships. He says that ships are known as "she" because of their womanly curves. Grossman explains that the master shipfitters were Irish and had learned the skills in the United Kingdom. Grossman worked on the USS Missouri and was one of four "kids" on a platform for the christening and launch. In addition, Grossman talks about his father's interactions with the Mafia while selling pickles, the founding of Las Vegas, and other jobs he has had including driving a taxi cab in New York and running a catering truck in California. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Blueprints; California; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Taxicab drivers -- New York (State) -- New York; Food; Ship models; Warships; Organized crime; Religion and culture -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Shipbuilding |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Shipyards |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Street vendors |z New York (State) |z New York; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Missouri (Battleship: BB 63)
- Oral History Interview with Frances Haber, November 13, 2009; 2010.003.013
  Frances Haber (1923 - 2010) grew up in the Bedford-Stuyvesant and Williamsburg neighborhoods of Brooklyn. Both her parents moved to the United States at young ages, her mother from Russia and her father from Austria. After graduating from Eastern District High School, Haber attended beauty school and worked briefly in her mother's beauty salon. Shortly after, she took an exam with the United States Civil Service Commission and worked for a short time before she moved with her family to California. Haber worked as a riveter for the Douglas Aircraft Company for a few months, after which she returned to Brooklyn, where she stayed with family until she found her own apartment at the age of 20. After leaving her position as a clerk typist for the pipefitter supervisors at the Navy Yard in 1945, Haber was one of the first two women to become a transit police officer. She also worked for the US Customs Service and eventually moved from Brooklyn to Croton-on-Hudson, New York.
  Frances Haber (1923- 2010) worked at the Brooklyn Navy Yard for several years, until she was laid off just after the end of WWII. In her interview, she recalls many details about her life in Brooklyn and the short time she spent in California, recollecting specific names, job titles, addresses and dates. Haber talks about growing up during the Depression, listening to the radio, her relationship with her mother and sister and local foods and restaurants. She also describes the ethnic makeup of her neighborhood and school and often brings up her Jewish background. Haber also describes the work she did at the Navy Yard as a clerk typist for the pipefitter supervisors, where she was often the only woman and fondly remembers eating lunch with the friendly supervisors. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Beauty parlors; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); California; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Family life -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Friendship; Great Depression |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Judaism; Local transit -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Race discrimination; Security systems; Transportation; Work environment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.). Eastern District High School
- Oral History Interview with Robert Hammond, September 9, 2010; 2010.003.032
  Robert S. Hammond (1926- ) grew up in Philadelphia, PA, in a predominantly Italian neighborhood. His mother is African- and Native- American from a tribal-owned island off the coast of South Carolina and his father is African- and European-American and also from the South. Hammond enlisted in the Navy in 1943 when he was 17 years old. After joining the Navy choir, he was selected as one of seven African American men from his group to be enrolled in the Hospital Corps School. This was the first group of African American men to be enrolled in the medical training. He was later transferred to the Montford Point Marine base in North Carolina, the first base for black marines. After he left the Navy, Hammond moved to Brooklyn and completed high school at Boys High. He opened a restaurant and nightclub on Fulton Street in Bedford Stuyvesant. Hammond went to a historically black college and got his Master's in Public Health from the University of Michigan. He has had a long career in public health in California and elsewhere, for which he credits his medical training in the Navy and experiences at Montford Point.
  During his interview, Robert S. Hammond (1926- ) discusses his experiences working for the Navy in Brooklyn and North Carolina. He mentions that he did not experience much racism until he spent some time in South Carolina when he was a teenager and talks about his shock and anger during these experiences. He explains that the Navy training at the time was segregated and that he experienced racism from some of the commanding officers. Navy hospitals were also segregated at the time and, Hammond explains, that black men in the military were not receiving equal health care. He describes his experiences at the New York Naval Hospital in the Brooklyn Navy Yard where he received further training before being transferred to the Montford Point Marine base in North Carolina. At Montford, Hammond took on many healthcare initiatives for the thousands of black Marines whose health was neglected because of the segregation and discrimination in southern healthcare. These initiatives included education and awareness about vaccinations, parasites, venereal disease, hygiene, and many other public health missions. While on leave, Hammond came down with appendicitis and was taken to the New York Naval Hospital where he had trained. While he was at the Hospital, a curtain was pulled around his bed to segregate him from the rest of the (white) ward and he recalls the hospital staff's reaction to his mother's visit since she looks white. He also describes visits from Helen Keller and Anne Sullivan, and the actor Frederic March. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  African Americans; South Carolina; North Carolina; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Philadelphia (Pa.); Health education; Hospitals; Military hospitals; Jazz; Marines; Musicians; Warships; Race relations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Racism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; World War, 1939-1945; New York Naval Shipyard; U.S. Naval Hospital (New York, N.Y.); Boys' High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Pearl Hill, February 20, 2007; 2010.003.034
  Pearl Margolis Hill (1923- ) grew up in the Middle Village neighborhood of Queens. She attended Grover Cleveland High School and two years at Queens College. After her husband joined the Army in 1940 or 1941, Hill decided to work at the Brooklyn Navy Yard in order to contribute to the war effort. She has two sons and currently lives in Florida.
  In her interview, Pearl Margolis Hill (1923- ) details her work at the Brooklyn Navy Yard as a shipfitter in Building 4 and her later work in the mold loft after an injury. She fondly remembers her friends at the Navy Yard, seeing them in passing on Sands Street and working alongside other married and unmarried women as welders. She also talks about working the graveyard shift, writing to her husband, what she wore to work and her longtime friendship with Sidonia Levine (2010.003.035, shipfitter). Interview conducted by Jennifer Egan.